Finding Aid for Medical School (University of Michigan) records, 1850-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Dean's Records 1915-1996
  - Committee and Council Series 1930-1996
    The arrangement, established by the Dean's office, of the 1930-1980 subseries (the original accessions) is a complicated one. Committees are arranged alphabetically by the source of their appointment. Thus committee records are divided by those committees appointed solely within the Medical School (Ad Hoc and Standing), committees appointed jointly by the Medical Center (Medical School and University Hospital), committees appointed by senior university administrators, and non-university committees, usually state or national committees in which the Medical School participated. In later accessions the distinguishing categories were abandoned. The records of the Executive Committee constitute a separate subseries.
    Among the most informative records in the Committee and Council Series are minutes of the Dean's Advisory Council, filed under the Medical School Standing Committees. The Dean's Advisory Council is composed of the heads of the various departments. Its minutes are generally complete between 1959 and 1977 and are remarkably informative and frank. Other significant committee files include: Building Committee, Interim Review and Promotion Board, 1930-1975; the Biomedical Research Council, 1974-1984; the Computer Advisory Committee, 1977-1983; Michigan Association for Regional Medical Planning, 1972-1973; and the Wayne County General Hospital Senior Advisory Group, 1965-1972.
    - 1930-1981
      - Medical School Committees (Ad Hoc)
        - Advanced Placement 1968-1971 (Box 1)
        - Appointments, Promotions & Titles 1967-1969 (Box 1)
        - Basic Science Clinical Phase 1972-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Biological Chemistry Chairman Search 1954, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - Biological Chemistry Review and Search 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Biomechanical Area (Highway Safety) 1966 (Box 1)
        - Biomedical Sciences 1969-1970 (Box 1)
        - Biophysics Research Chairman Search 1960-1961 (Box 1)
        - Building
          - Animal Research Facility 1961-1963 (Box 1)
          - Children's Hospital 1957-1966 (Box 1)
          - Clinical Research Center 1961 (Box 1)
          - Kresge Hearing Research Institute 1960-1963 (Box 1)
          - Kresge Medical Science II (addition)
            - Minutes 1959-1964 (Box 1)
            - Dean's Conference Minutes 1962-1967 (Box 1)
            - Faculty Committee Minutes 1963-1965 (Box 2)
            - Preliminary Planning (Box 2)
            - Plan of July 16, 1963 (Box 2)
            - Plan of October 1, 1963 (Box 2)
            - Holabird & Root Plan September 30, 1963 (Box 2)
            - Grant Application June 30, 1964 (Box 2)
            - General (Box 2)
        - Cancer Coordinator 1959-1971 (Box 2)
        - Clinical Curriculum Planning 1970 (Box 2)
        - Clinical Titles, Policies and Procedures 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        - Compensatory Year Program Planning 1970 (Box 2)
        - Curriculum Appraisal 1969-1972 (Box 2)
        - Data Systems Policy Advisory 1970 (Box 2)
        - Economics of Health Care, Curricular Aspects 1977-1978 (Box 2)
        - Electrographic Technology Program 1973 (Box 2)
        - Evaluation by Students 1963-1965 (Box 2)
        - Faculty Planning Committee of Kresge Medical Science II [See Building Committee, Kresge Medical Science II (addition)] (Box 2)
        - Faculty Titles 1961-1966 (Box 2)
        - Freshman Clinic 1959-1967 (Box 2)
        - Future of Curriculum in Forensic Medicine 1963-1966 (Box 2)
        - Governance Clarification 1978 (Box 2)
        - Grade Reporting 1964-1965 (Box 2)
        - Graduate Medical Education 1974 (Box 2)
        - "Let's Move Group" (Medical Center Planning) 1970-1971 (Box 2)
        - Masters Program, Identification of Review Mechanism 1964-1966 (Box 2)
        - MD Degree "With Distinction," 1963 (Box 2)
        - Medical Student Health Services 1964-1967 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Neural and Behavioral Science 1969-1970 (Box 2)
        - Neuropathology Faculty Policy 1960 (Box 2)
        - Neuropathology Laboratories 1959-1961 (Box 2)
        - Postgraduate Medicine Review 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Primate Center Planning 1960-1961 (Box 2)
        - Program Planning, Office of, Director Search 1969-1970 (Box 3)
        - Psychiatry Review ca. 1962
          - General (Box 3)
          - Appendix, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Background, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Recognition of Distinguished Faculty 1961-1963 (Box 3)
        - Renal Dialysis 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - Research Policy 1963-1964 (Box 3)
        - Review of Policies: Off Campus Assignment of Trainees 1964-1970 (Box 3)
        - Senior Selective Program 1961-1967 (Box 3)
        - Sesquicentennial (Medical School) 1965-1967 (Box 3)
        - Sex Education 1964-1965 (Box 3)
        - Simpson Memorial Institute, Committee to Examine the Purpose of 1962 (Box 3)
        - Student Center 1970-1971 (Box 3)
        - Student Dress 1961-1967 (Box 3)
        - Student Research 1970-1971 (Box 3)
        - Transplantation of Whole Organs, Policy Committee 1969-1971 (Box 3)
        - Uniform Schedules for Clinical Assignments on Holidays 1967 (Box 3)
      - Medical School Committees (Standing)
        - Academics Programs 1964-1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Admissions 1960-1969 (Box 3)
        - Advanced Placement 1969-1971 (Box 3)
        - Animal Care 1962-1969 (Box 3)
        - Athletic Injuries 1959-1964 (Box 3)
        - Audiovisual Education 1963-1970 (Box 4)
        - Biomedical Data Processing, Development of 1962-1965 (Box 4)
        - Biomedical Engineering 1970 (Box 4)
        - Cancer Research 1960-1970 (Box 4)
        - Central Tissue Culture 1969 (Box 4)
        - Community Medicine Committees and Program
          - General 1970 (Box 4)
          - Advisory Committee 1968-1969 (Box 4)
          - Correspondence 1968-1969 (Box 4)
          - Comprehensive Care Clinical Plan 1966-1968 (Box 4)
          - Dean of Medical School, Report to June 17, 1969 (Box 4)
          - Director of Program 1968-1969 (Box 4)
          - Family Health Care Facility 1965-1969 (Box 4)
          - Free Peoples Clinic 1970-1973 (Box 4)
          - Grand Rapids Area Medical Education Center (GRAMEC) 1970-1971 (Box 4)
          - Instructional Program 1968-1969 (Box 4)
          - Policy Committee 1968-1969 (Box 4)
          - Primary Care Preceptorship Program
            - 1969-1972 (Box 4)
            - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
          - Research Advisory Committee (Box 5)
          - Veterans Administration Hospital (Box 5)
        - Compensatory Year Program Planning 1969 (Box 5)
        - Computer Activities Advisory 1969 (Box 5)
        - Concurrent Examination, First and Second Years 1968-1969 (Box 5)
        - Curriculum 1959-1968 (Box 5)
        - Curriculum Policy 1960-1963 (Box 5)
        - Dean's Advisory Council
          - 1959-1971 (Box 5)
          - January 1973-May 1976, 5 folders (Box 5)
          - June 1976-August 1977, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1930-1984
      - Interim Review and Promotion Board Minutes
        The Interim Review and Promotion Board, at first called simply the Promotion Board, evaluated the academic performance of medical students and recommended that a student be promoted to the next year of study or that the student seek remedial help or counseling. The minutes often contain very frank assessments of students' academic records and of their psychological and social adjustment to medical school. This subseries is not open for research.
        - 1930-1931
          - Freshmen (Box 144)
          - Juniors (Box 144)
        - 1932-1947
          - Freshmen (Box 144)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
          - Sophomore (Box 144)
          - Junior (Box 144)
        - 1948-1959
          - Freshmen (Box 144)
            [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2034 ]
          - Sophomores (Box 145)
          - Juniors (Box 145)
        - 1951-1959 (Box 145)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 145)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2035 ]
        - 1961-1967 (Box 145)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2042 ]
        - 1962-1963 (Box 145)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2038 ]
        - 1963-1964 (Box 145)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2039 ]
        - 1965-1965 (Box 146)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2040 ]
        - 1965-1966 (Box 146)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2041 ]
          (1966-67 missing)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 146)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2043 ]
        - 1968-1969 (Box 146)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2044 ]
        - 1969-1970 (Box 146)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2045 ]
        - Deficiencies 1967-1970 (Box 146)
        - April-August 1971 (Box 147)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2046 ]
        - October 1971-March 3, 1972 (Box 147)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2047 ]
        - March 3-August 1972 (Box 147)
        - October 1972-February 1973 (Box 148)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2048 ]
        - March-November 20, 1973 (Box 148)
        - October 1973-February 21, 1974 (Box 148)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2049 ]
        - March 19-September 30, 1974 (Box 148)
        - October 1974-August 1975 (Box 149)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2050 ]
      - Bio-Medical Research Council Minutes
        The Biomedical Research Council (BMRC) is an inter-departmental committee that reviews faculty research proposals in the biomedical field. The BMRC minutes include research proposals, budgets, and the Council's evaluation of proposals. The Computer Advisory Committee ascertained Medical School and Hospital computer needs and coordinated medical computing activity with the University Computing Center. The Michigan Association for Regional Medical Planning (MARMP) and the Wayne County General Hospital (WCGH) Senior Advisory Group subseries both complement records from the earlier accession.
        - 1974
          - July 19-September 3 (Box 150)
          - September 20-27 (Box 150)
          - October 4-November 1 (Box 150)
          - November 8-December 29 (Box 150)
        - 1975
          - January 3-February 21 (Box 150)
          - February 28-March 28 (Box 150)
          - April 4-May 8 (Box 150)
          - June 6-September 26 (Box 150)
          - October 3-December 19 (Box 150)
        - 1976
          - January 16-April 23 (Box 150)
          - May 7-December 10 (Box 150)
        - 1977
          - January 21-April 22 (Box 150)
          - May 6-July 15 (Box 150)
          - July 22-August 26 (Box 150)
          - September 9-October 21 (Box 150)
          - November 4-December 23 (Box 150)
        - 1978
          - January 6-27 (Box 150)
          - February 10-24 (Box 150)
          - March 3-31 (Box 150)
          - April 7-21 (Box 150)
          - May 5-22 (Box 150)
          - June 2 (Box 150)
          - June 9-16 (Box 150)
          - June 23-30 (Box 150)
          - July 14-28 (Box 151)
          - August 4-September 28 (Box 151)
          - October 6-27 (Box 151)
        - 1979
          - January 5-12 (Box 151)
          - January 19-26 (Box 151)
          - February 16 (Box 151)
          - February 23, 2 folders (Box 151)
          - March 2 (Box 151)
          - March 9-30 (Box 151)
          - April 6-27 (Box 151)
          - May 11-25 (Box 151)
          - June 1-15 (Box 151)
          - June 22-29 (Box 151)
          - July 13-24 (Box 151)
          - August 3-9 (Box 151)
          - August 17-September 7 (Box 151)
          - September 21-September 28 (Box 151)
          - October 12 (Box 151)
          - October 26 (Box 151)
          - November 9-December 14 (Box 151)
        - 1980
          - January 11-February 1 (Box 152)
          - February 15-22 (Box 152)
          - February 29-March 14 (Box 152)
          - April 11 (Box 152)
          - April 18-May 2 (Box 152)
          - May 9-30 (Box 152)
          - June 6-13 (Box 152)
          - June 27 (Box 152)
          - July 18 (Box 152)
          - August 1 (Box 152)
          - August 29 (Box 152)
          - September 5-19 (Box 152)
          - September 26-October 3 (Box 152)
          - October 10-October 24 (Box 152)
          - October 31 (Box 152)
          - November 7-14 (Box 152)
          - December 5-12 (Box 152)
        - 1981
          - January 9-February 13 (Box 152)
          - March 6-27 (Box 152)
          - April 3-24 (Box 152)
          - May 8 (Box 152)
          - May 22-29 (Box 152)
          - June 5 (Box 153)
          - June 12-26 (Box 153)
          - July 10-24 (Box 153)
          - July 31 (Box 153)
          - August 7-September 11 (Box 153)
          - September 18-25 (Box 153)
          - October 2-9 (Box 153)
          - October 23-November 13 (Box 153)
          - November 20-December 4 (Box 153)
          - December 11-18 (Box 153)
          - January 8-22 (Box 153)
          - February 2, 2 folders (Box 153)
          - February 12-19 (Box 153)
          - March 5-19 (Box 153)
          - March 26-April 9 (Box 153)
          - April 23-30 (Box 153)
          - May 7-28 (Box 153)
          - June 4-18 (Box 153)
          - June 25-July 2 (Box 153)
          - July 23 (Box 153)
          - July 30-September 10 (Box 154)
          - September 17-24 (Box 154)
          - October 1-22 (Box 154)
          - October 29 (Box 154)
          - November 5-12 (Box 154)
          - December 3 (Box 154)
          - December 10 (Box 154)
          - December 17 (Box 154)
        - 1983
          - January 7 (Box 154)
          - January 14-28 (Box 154)
          - February 11-25 (Box 154)
          - March 4-25 (Box 154)
          - April 1-29 (Box 154)
          - May 13-20 (Box 154)
          - June 3 (Box 154)
          - June 17 (Box 154)
          - July 15 (Box 154)
          - July 29 (Box 154)
          - September 9 (Box 154)
          - September 23-October 14 (Box 154)
          - October 21-28 (Box 154)
          - November 4-11 (Box 154)
          - November 18 (Box 155)
          - December 2 (Box 155)
          - December 9, 1983-January 13, 1984 (Box 155)
      - Committee on Locus of EEG Unit 1975 (Box 155)
      - Computer Advisory Committee Minutes
        - December 1977-1978 (Box 155)
        - January-April 1979 (Box 155)
        - May-June 1979 (Box 155)
        - October-December 1979 (Box 155)
        - January-April 1980 (Box 155)
        - May-September 1980 (Box 155)
        - October-December 1980 (Box 155)
        - February-March 1981 (Box 155)
        - April-November 1981 (Box 155)
        - January-May 1982 (Box 155)
        - July-September 1982 (Box 155)
        - October 1982-April 1983 (Box 155)
        - September-November 1983 (Box 155)
      - Michigan Association for Regional Medical Program (MARMP)
        - Board of Directors Meeting (see also boxes 26-30)
          - July 21, 1972 (Box 156)
          - August 18, 1972 (Box 156)
          - September 22-October 20, 1972 (Box 156)
          - December 1, 1972 (Box 156)
          - June 16, 1973 (Box 156)
        - Correspondence and Memoranda, 2 folders (Box 156)
        - Grant Applications
          - November 1971 (Box 156)
          - July 1972 (Box 156)
        - Regional Advisory Group Meetings September 1972-January 1973 (Box 156)
      - University of Michigan General Surgery Associates (Box 156)
      - Wayne County General Hospital (WCGH) (see also box 24)
        - Senior Advisory Group Minutes 1965-1972, 4 folders (Box 156)
    - 1977-1990
      - Executive Faculty Minutes
        - January 1977-February 1981, 7 volumes (Box 248)
        - March 1981-November 1989, 8 volumes (Box 249)
      - Dean's Advisory Committee on Clinical Affairs (DACCA) (Box 250)
        - 1986 (Box 250)
      - Dean's Advisory Council
        - September 1977-April 1985, 6 volumes (Box 250)
        - May 1985-June 1990, 2 volumes (Box 251)
      - Dean's Council of Clinical Chairmen (DCCC)
        - November 1986-October 1989 (Box 251)
      - Joint Staff (University Hospitals/Medical School)
        - June 1985-October 1986, 2 volumes (Box 251)
        - November 1986-December 1989, 6 volumes (Box 252)
    - 1987-1996
      - Medical School Executive Faculty (MSEF)
        - 1990, 1 volumes (Box 269)
          [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
        - 1991-1995, 1 folders; 4 volumes (Box 270)
      - Medical Service Plan (MSP) Visiting Committee 1987-1989 (Box 270)
      - Medical Service Plan Advisory Committee (MSP AC)
        - 1989-1992 1995, 7 folders (Box 270)
          (Missing 1993 and 1994)
        - January-June 1996 (Box 271)
      - Medical Service Plan Executive Committee (MSP EC)
        - 1989-1995, 13 folders (Box 271)
        - January-June 1996, 2 folders (Box 272)
      - Clinical Delivery Service (CDS) Executive Committee May 1995-December 1996, 14 folders (Box 272)
      - Faculty Group Practice Board July-December 1996, 5 folders (Box 273)
      - [Hospital/Dean's Office] Joint Staff Meetings
        - July 1990-December 1992, 9 folders (Box 273)
          (Missing January-March, 1991)
        - 1993-1994, 8 folders (Box 274)
        - Dean's Staff Meetings 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 274)
  - Executive Committee 1930-2000
    The records of the Medical School Executive Committee include a run of that body's minutes, from its founding in 1930 through 2000. The records also include two small files relating to appointments and promotions and committee retreats. The primary record of the school's governing body, the minutes provide documentation of a wide array of policies, programs and issues.
    As the School's presumptive court of last appeal, the Medical School Executive Committee routinely decided whether students should be dismissed from the school, or allowed re-admittance after a dismissal. Moreover, it heard students' appeals of these decisions. Similarly, it had final say over faculty appointments, promotion, and tenure decisions, and also heard departmental chair appeals of negative decisions on any of these matters. Because all of the above issues were carefully documented with significant amounts of personal information, the Medical School Executive Committee records are under extended restrictions.
    - Full Committee Minutes
      - February 1930-December 1955, 4 volumes (Box 6)
      - January 1956-August 1968, 7 volumes (Box 7)
      - September 1968-December 1970, 7 volumes (Box 8)
      - January 1971-May 1972, 5 volumes (Box 9)
      - June 1972-August 1973, 5 volumes (Box 10)
      - September 1973-July 1974, 5 volumes (Box 11)
      - July 1974-October 1975, 7 volumes (Box 12)
      - October 1975-April 1976, 6 volumes (Box 13)
      - April-December 1976 (Box 14)
      - January 1977-April 1977, 5 volumes (Box 137)
      - April 1977-September 1977, 5 volumes (Box 138)
      - September 1977-February 1978, 5 volumes (Box 139)
      - February 1978-June 1978, 5 volumes (Box 140)
      - June 1978-September 1978, 5 volumes (Box 141)
      - September 1978-February 1979, 5 volumes (Box 142)
      - March 1979-June 1979, 5 volumes (Box 143)
      - 1979
        - July 19-September 20, 1979 (Box 200)
        - September 27-November 8, 1979 (Box 200)
        - November 15-December 20, 1979 (Box 200)
      - 1980
        - January 10-January 31, 1980 (Box 201)
        - February 7, 1980 (Box 201)
        - February 14-March 13, 1980 (Box 201)
        - April 3-May 15, 1980 (Box 201)
        - May 22-June 26, 1980 (Box 201)
        - July 3-August 31, 1980 (Box 202)
        - September 4-October 9, 1980 (Box 202)
        - October 16-November 20, 1980 (Box 202)
        - November 26-December 18, 1980 (Box 202)
      - 1981
        - January 8-January 15, 1981 (Box 202)
        - January 22-January 29, 1981 (Box 203)
        - February 5-February 20, 1981 (Box 203)
        - February 26-March 26, 1981 (Box 203)
        - April 2-May 7, 1981 (Box 203)
        - May 14-June 4, 1981 (Box 203)
        - June 11-July 16, 1981 (Box 204)
        - July 23-August 13, 1981 (Box 204)
        - August 27-September 17, 1981 (Box 204)
        - September 24-October 15, 1981 (Box 204)
        - October 29-November 19, 1981 (Box 204)
        - December 3, 1981 (Box 205)
        - December 10-December 17, 1981 (Box 205)
      - 1982
        - January 7-January 14 1982 (Box 205)
        - January 21-January 28 1982 (Box 205)
        - February 4-February 18 1982 (Box 205)
        - February 24-March 25 1982 (Box 206)
        - April 8-April 15 1982 (Box 206)
        - April 22-May 13, 1982 (Box 206)
        - May 20-June 17, 1982 (Box 206)
        - July 7-August 19, 1982 (Box 206)
        - September 2-September 30, 1982 (Box 207)
        - October 7-November 4, 1982 (Box 207)
      - 1983
        - November 11-December 16 (Box 207)
        - January 13-February 3 (Box 207)
        - February 10-February 24 (Box 207)
        - March 17 (Box 208)
        - March 24-May 5 (Box 208)
        - May 12-June 16 (Box 208)
        - July 10-July 21 (Box 208)
        - August 18-September 1 (Box 208)
        - September 5-October 13 (Box 209)
        - October 27-November 17 (Box 209)
        - December 8-December 22 (Box 209)
      - 1984
        - January 4-19 (Box 239)
        - January 26-February 9 (Box 239)
        - March 1-29 (Box 239)
        - April 19-May 10 (Box 239)
        - May 24-31 (Box 239)
        - June 21-28 (Box 239)
        - July 5-19 (Box 239)
        - July 21-August 16 (Box 239)
        - August 30-September 28 (Box 240)
        - October 4-November 8 (Box 240)
        - November 15-29 (Box 240)
        - December 6-20, 1984 (Box 240)
      - 1985
        - January 11-24 (Box 240)
        - January 31-February 21 (Box 240)
        - February 28-March 28 (Box 241)
        - April 4-May 9 (Box 241)
        - May 23-June 27 (Box 241)
        - July 11-August 29 (Box 241)
        - September 5-October 10 (Box 241)
        - October 17-November 21 (Box 241)
        - December 12-19 (Box 242)
      - 1986
        - January 2-23, 1986 (Box 242)
        - January 30-March 20 (Box 242)
        - March 27-April 24 (Box 242)
        - May 1-22 (Box 242)
        - June 5-19 (Box 242)
        - "Grandfathering" Requests for Instructional Sequence Faculty (Box 242)
        - June 26-August 21 (Box 243)
        - September 4-October 9 (Box 243)
        - October 16-November 20 (Box 243)
        - December 4-11 (Box 243)
        - December 18 (Box 243)
      - 1987
        - January 8 (Box 243)
        - January 15-29 (Box 243)
        - February 5-12 (Box 244)
        - March 5-April 16 (Box 244)
        - April 30-May 28 (Box 244)
        - June 24-July 2 (Box 244)
        - July 9-August 29 (Box 244)
        - September 24-October 29 (Box 244)
        - November 12-December 10 (Box 244)
        - December 17 (Box 245)
      - 1988
        - January 21 (Box 245)
        - January 28-February 25 (Box 245)
        - March 10-April 21 (Box 245)
        - May 12-June 30 (Box 245)
        - July 14-August 25 (Box 245)
        - September 15-October 27 (Box 246)
        - November 3-17 (Box 246)
        - December 1-22 (Box 246)
      - 1989
        - January 5 (Box 246)
        - January 15-February 26 (Box 246)
        - March 9-20 (Box 246)
        - April 27-June 22 (Box 247)
        - July 6-August 24 (Box 247)
        - September 11-November 16 (Box 247)
        - November 30-December 21 (Box 247)
      - January-September 6, 1990, 9 folders (Box 260)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2065 ]
      - September 13, 1990-May 2, 1991, 4 folders (Box 261)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2066 ]
      - May 16 1991-January 23, 1992, 4 folders (Box 262)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2067 ]